Guide to the Gorham Munson Papers on the American Social Credit Movement and New Democracy, 1899 - 1969, bulk 1932 - 1945
Gorham Munson Papers on the American Social Credit Movement and New Democracy, 1899 - 1969, bulk 1932 - 1945
Gorham Munson was the most eloquent and durable Social Credit leader in the United States. In 1932, he became American correspondent for The New English Weekly, defended Social Credit in The Nation and helped form a key Social Credit organization, the New Economics Group of New York. In 1933 he initiated a vital Social Credit journal of the arts and public affairs, New Democracy, and was its chief editor during its three-year life. Beginning in 1935, Munson was an active lobbyist working with such congressmen as T. Alan Goldsborough and Jerry F. Voorhis in seeking national Social Credit legislation. During the middle thirties there were short lived or temporary organizations, national in scope, that espoused Social Credit, among them the National Social Credit Association, the League for National Dividends and the Committee in Support of H. R. 7188. In 1938 Munson led convinced Social Crediters in the formation of a more permanent organization, the American Social Credit Movement (ASCM), for which he served as General Secretary throughout its existence from 1938 to 1945.
ASCM encountered several difficulties in spreading Social Credit in the United States. Its membership was limited to persons subscribing to the Douglas Theorem and three specific national legislative goals, which meant that some independent Social Crediters and hosts of plain money reformers were excluded. Social Credit bills in Congress were diluted and became progressively less satisfactory to the ASCM. New Deal reforms and the coming of World War II lessened interest in basic economic change. Some money reformers, including Ezra Pound and Major Douglas, became loudly anti-Semitic. This Munson dealt with squarely and courageously but, even so, the Social Credit movement in the United States ended, chiefly due to the War.
In 1945 Munson published a book entitled Aladdin's Lamp: The Wealth of the American People summing up his critique of the private monopoly of banks which held down the credit power of the American people.
THE ROLE OF A. R. ORAGE, 1931-1934. The importance of A. R. Orage in the Social Credit movement in England has been remarked upon above. This exceptional man also played an important role in the formation of the movement among American intellectuals as a sponsor of the ideas of the Gurdjieff system. This occurred during the late 1920s when he travelled between New York and Fontainebleau. In New York he organized groups for instruction in the Gurdjieff system and there met Gorham Munson, Elizabeth Delza, Margaret Anderson, Jane Heap, Van Wyck Brooks, Lawrence S. Morris and others. At the depth of the Great Depression Orage again drew upon his knowledge of Social Credit to win American intellectuals to this view, as Munson has recalled: Shortly before the end of his American stay, Orage took the initiative and rented a room at the New York School of the Theatre to give a series of four lectures on Social Credit in the early part of 1931. About fifty enrolled to hear his plea that Financial Credit reflect Real Credit. He also struck a note for increasing the distribution of leisure, defined as the economic condition of voluntary activity. Orage left the United States soon afterwards to return to England where he established the New English Weekly. In New York a study group under the leadership of Schuyler Jackson began meeting at Muriel Draper's home, and from this group of enthusiasts came the founders of the New Economics Group of New York in the fall of 1932. [Gorham Munson, The Awakening Twenties, Brom Weber, editor, Berkeley and Los Angeles: University of California Press, forthcoming 1977.]
NEW ENGLISH WEEKLY, 1932-1947. Begun in London on April 21, 1932, the New English Weekly under A. R. Orage sought a wide audience for its Social Credit message. Major Douglas, Ezra Pound and Orage--whom T. S. Eliot called a tireless and wholly disinterested evangelist of monetary reform--were frequently featured. NEW was a clearinghouse for the movement through its Credit Forum carrying organizational news from all countries. Gorham Munson was on the masthead from the very first issue as American Representative. Through its circulation here Munson helped crystallize activity for Social Credit in the United States. [See Gorham Munson, American Intelligentsia, Advance, New English Weekly, Vol. 2, Dec. 29, 1932.]
NEW ECONOMICS GROUP OF NEW YORK, 1932-1938. A number of valuable functions were performed by the New Economics Group of New York following its formation in December, 1932. Its study meetings broadened knowledge of Social Credit. It sponsored and provided editorial and business offices for New Democracy. Its technical committee drafted the National Credit Issue Bill, a model for bills introduced for legislative consideration in Washington, London, and Ottawa. It conducted major public lectures on the subject of Social Credit: Archibald MacLeish in 1933, Major C. H. Douglas in 1934, and the Very Reverent Hewlett Johnson, Dean of Canterbury in 1935. Board members included Allan R. Brown, Blanche Brownell Grant, Paul Hampden, Elizabeth Sage Holter, Lawrence Morris, Gorham Munson, and W. A. Nyland. After 1935 the New Economics Group of New York experienced a decline caused in part by personal disagreements and factionalism.
NEW DEMOCRACY, 1933-1936. A fortnightly and later monthly review of economics and the arts, New Democracy was published in New York for three years beginning August 15, 1933. Its announced policy was Social Credit in the United States at the earliest possible date. To achieve this, New Democracy's columns were packed full with Social Credit -- news notes, articles, poems, letters, book reviews and organizational items. This review also published major documents of the movement in the United States: the text of speeches by Major douglas and the Dean of Canterbury, the Goldsborough Social Credit Bill and significant commentary. Gorham Munson was the editor throughout the three years, joined by Herbert Bruce Brougham in 1933-1934, by Lawrence Morris in 1934-1935, and by Paul Hampden and Elliott Taylor in 1935-1936. W. A. Nyland of the New Economics Group of New York was the publisher.
NEW DIRECTIONS, 1935-1936. Under Munson, New Democracy in its final year of publication included a distinguished literary page with the title New Directions, edited by James Laughlin IV. Scion of the Pittsburgh steel family, in 1935 a student at Harvard, Laughlin had been introduced to Munson by Ezra Pound. He opened the page with this declaration: New Directions. The great new direction is, of course, Social Credit, with its changed conception of the means, and the ends of life. Not all contributions dealt with economics or Social Credit, however, as Laughlin published T. S. Eliot, Marianne Moore, Henry Miller, e. e. cummings and Kay Boyle. Pound's great Bank of England CANTO, XLVI, which Laughlin called definitely the epic of Social Credit, was published in the March, 1936 issue of New Democracy. The literary page ended, but its name was adopted by Laughlin for his avant-garde New Directions publishing house.
NATIONAL SOCIAL CREDIT ASSOCIATION, 1934-1935. In 1934 W. A. Nyland of the New Economics Group of New York tried to federate local organizations across the United States into the National Social Credit Association. His capacity for leadership was insufficient, and established local independence prevailed. Philadelphia's Retail Discount Organization, formed in 1931 and led by Edward F. Harvey, was the oldest Social Credit local in the country. Others were New Economics Groups led by Social Credit pioneers: Herbert Bruce Brougham in Washington, Mrs. E. Sohier Welch in Boston, Luther Whiteman in San Francisco, J. Crate Larkin in Buffalo, and A. M. Edwards in Detroit. There were smaller groups in Carmel, Los Gatos, and Pasadena, California; West Palm Beach, Florida; Peekskill, New York; and Colorado Springs, Colorado. These organizations continued even after the National Social Credit Association failed in 1935.
LEAGUE FOR NATIONAL DIVIDENDS, 1935-1936. Formed in San Francisco in June 1935, by Elliott Taylor, editor of the magazine Controversy, the League for National Dividends aimed to build up a mass-demand for the issuance to al of national dividends. Following the Social Credit sweep in Alberta Province on August 22, 1935, and the introduction of the Goldsborough Bill in Congress, the headquarters of the League for National Dividends was moved to the offices of New Democracy in New York. Soon Gorham Munson was Acting Secretary, council members included Howard Buck, Walter Hampden and William Carlos Williams, and the League spoke militantly: WANTED: SOCIAL CREDIT SHOCK TROOPS. Low productivity was attributed to the lack of consumer purchasing power. The League argued that new money must be issued by the Government as potential production warrants it. There is no evidence of a rise of interest in Social Credit on account of the League. There were only brief hearings on the Goldsborough Bill and 1935, and by August 1936, the League for National Dividends had dissolved.
GOLDSBOROUGH SOCIAL CREDIT BILL, H.R. 9216, 74th CONGRESS, 1935-1936. Congressman T. Alan Goldsborough (D., Md.) in August 1935, sponsored the first bill embodying Social Credit principles to be introduced in any legislative body in the United States. This was largely in the form drafted by a committee of the New Economics Group of New York consisting of Allan R. Brown, Edward F. Harvey, W. A. Nyland, Carle C. Conway, Jr., and H. B. Brougham. Its short title was the National Income and Credit Issue Bill introduced on August 22 and, as Brougham wrote in New Democracy, embodying the tenets of Douglas without any frills. The bill presents straight out Social Credit measures. It would establish the National Credit Account, defined in Title I as the money valuation of the annual unused capacity of the industries and people of the United States to produce wanted goods and services. The Treasury would produce non-interest bearing credit certificates, not to exceed the National Credit Account, to circulate as money throughout the banking system only. These certificates would finance a discount on prices to consumers at retail. They would also provide a national per capita consumers dividend of $5.00 a month. This consumers' dividend and other features of the bill would be administered by an independent regulatory agency called the Federal Credit Commission. Should the Commission records show an unduly expanded monetary condition then a Credit Retirement Fund would set aside a portion of national revenues to retire Treasury credit certificates. The bill was discussed and analyzed at length in New Democracy, advocated by the League for National Dividends and, with Goldsborough as the ranking member of the House Committee on Banking and Currency, there were brief hearings on H.R. 9216 in the 74th Congress. On this occasion, Paul Hampden testified for the Social Credit bill at the invitation of Goldsborough. The bill lapsed at the end of the 1936 session.
COMMITTEE IN SUPPORT OF H.R. 7188, 1937-1938. Twenty Social Crediters formed the ad hoc Committee in Support of H.R. 7188, to lobby for Goldsborough's revised bill in the 76th Congress, 1937-1938. The final report of the Committee's Secretary, Gorham Munson, describes the frustrations experienced in seeking Social Credit legislation. The bill, H.R. 7188, had several basic weaknesses: it neglected the crucial fact of an inherent shortage of money in consumers' hands and it presented the retail price discount as merely an emergency device for economic slumps to be snapped off on recovery. Although Munson twice testified, the hearings were not satisfactory from his viewpoint. Leading Social Credit figures who were members of the Committee in Support of H.R. 7188--Wallace Clark, Raymond Haight, J. Crate Larkin, C. E. Luntz, Allan T. Gwathmey and Elliott Taylor--did not appear. Yet, three whom Munson regarded as eclectic Social Crediters--Allan R. Brown, Herbert Bruce Brougham and Edward F. Harvey--participated in the hearings. Munson interviewed several congressmen in Washington. Paul Hampden acted as technical adviser to the Committee. Mrs. E. Sohier Welch served as Treasurer. Despite disappointment, Munson praised the efforts of Congressman Goldsborough and concluded that future legislative efforts should not allow compromise with Social Credit Principles.
AMERICAN SOCIAL CREDIT MOVEMENT, 1938-1945. The culminating voluntary association promoting Social Credit in the United States was the American Social Credit Movement, founded on October 5, 1938. Gorham Munson was General Secretary. Paul Hampden served as Acting Secretary while Munson was on leave in Washington, 1939-1940. ASCM sought public support but limited its membership strictly to those who after sufficient acquaintance with the ideas of Social Credit are prepared to subscribe to the Theorem and the Three Demands. As a result of experience with the second Goldsborough Bill, the three demands were to establish the Federal Credit Commission, the Compensated Price and the National Dividend. Eclectic money reformers were thus excluded and membership in ASCM never reached one hundred. The American Social Credit Movement maintained a book service, sponsored lectures and study meetings, issued weekly bulletins and worked for legislation. Munson cooperated with Representative Jerry F. Voorhis (D., Cal.) in framing Social Credit bills in 1939-1940, 1941-1942 and 1943-1944. He also prepared a special series of bulletins on Social Credit called Men First. Activities diminished after 1942 and ceased altogether in 1945.
WILLIAM CARLOS WILLIAMS AND SOCIAL CREDIT, 1933-1941. The Rutherford, New Jersey, physician and poet William Carlos Williams (1883-1963) was a member of most of the Social Credit organizations led by Gorham Munson. Williams was persuaded to his Social Credit beliefs by Ezra Pound. He wrote for New Democracy, heard Major Douglas speak in New York in 1934, and was a member of the League for National Dividends and the American Social Credit Movement. Wile Williams had a continuing interest in Social Credit, he was not a very active participant in the organizations he joined. Williams joined Munson, Laughlin, Walter, Paul Hampden, and others in 1936 and the University of Virginia where he attacked bankers and declared that money reform would bestow cultural benefits. Pound's addiction to Fascism and Douglas's to anti-Semitism made Williams flee the Social Credit movement. [A good study is Reed Whittemore, William Carlos Williams: Poet from Jersey (Boston: Houghton Mifflin Company, 1975), pp. 259-264.]
EZRA POUND AND SOCIAL CREDIT, 1920-1945. American poet Ezra Pound (1885-1971) in the 1920s and 1930s argued insistently in prose and verse that usura, or credit capitalism, was the root of all evil in the world and Douglas Social Credit reforms was the best cure. This view permeated most of his writings especially the middle Cantos, of which CANTO XLV on usury, and CANTO XLVI on the Bank of England published in New Democracy are noteworthy. In 1920, he reviewed Douglas's Economic Democracy for an American audience in The Little Review. He wrote regularly for New Democracy, and numerous letters harangued Munson about Mussolini, Roosevelt, the New Deal, bankers, Jews and Social Credit. Pound left the United States in 1908, lived in England until 1920, in Paris until 1928, and Rapallo, Italy until 1945. After 1937, Munson did not think Pound to be a real Social Crediter. Pound attached himself to Social Credit while dabbling in other theories of money reforms. Because of his fascination with the Corporate State, and his ultimate lapse into anti-Semitism, he gave Social Credit a black eye. On account of paid broadcasts to American troops and related overt acts in wartime with the intent to adhere to and give aid and comfort to the Kingdom of Italy, and its military allies, Pound was indicted by the United States for felonious, traitorous and treasonable actions. Removed to Washington, Pound was found mentally incompetent to stand trial and so was confined to St. Elizabeth's Hospital from 1945 to 1958 when he was allowed to return to his home in Rapallo. [For some works explaining the context of Pound's economic thought, see Earle Davis, Vision Fugitive: Ezra Pound and Economics (Lawrence, Kansas: University Press of Kansas, 1968); Hugh Kenner, The Pound Era (Berkeley and Los Angeles: University of California Press, 1971); C. David Heymann, Ezra Pound: The Last Rower (New York: Viking Press, 1976).]
ANTI-SEMITISM IN SOCIAL CREDIT, 1938-1941. Gorham Munson led the American Social Credit Movement in repudiating those money reformers guilty of anti-Semitism by linking usury, banking and Jews together. ASCM took this official position:
American Social Credit stands for the liberty and equality of opportunity of the individual irrespective of race, creed or color. We abominate anti-Semitism. The Money Question and the so-called Jewish Question have NOTHING to do with each other and we will let no one confuse this fact.
Munson was obliged to apply this principle to Major C. H. Douglas, the originator of Social Credit, in 1938 and he did so with dispatch, disowning Douglas for anti-Semitism while staying pledged to Douglas economics. Munson also shed all responsibility for Ezra Pound well before the United States entered World War II. Munson was an outspoken critic of anti-Semitism in private correspondence and in public statements. [See Gorham Munson, A New Attack on Anti-Semitism, Opinion: A Journal of Jewish Life and Letters, September 1939.]
ALADDIN'S LAMP, 1945. As ASCM activities lessened during World War II, Munson completed a book criticizing the banking-credit system and advocating Social Credit as a vitally needed reform. The book, entitled Aladdin's Lamp: The Wealth of the American People, won favorable reviews and many laudatory letters. Its publication in the spring of 1945 marked the end of Munson's active advocacy of Social Credit and of the American Social Credit Movement. Munson had occasion, in answering a friendly letter questioning the value of Social Credit, to sum up his feelings about the reform he had championed actively since 1932:
Social Credit is not a cure-all. Our dogmatism goes only this far: we assert that credit reform must have priority over any other reforms; we assert it is fundamental. We can then tackle with some hope of success other bad features of capitalism. Beyond this are the psychological problems of the good life to which Social Credit provides no key. Even with Social Credit human nature would be plenty troublesome. But I do not think it would act, as does chronic money shortage, to whip people up to greed and war. On the contrary, it would give humane education a real chance--but only a chance. It can't accomplish what is ultimately the function of culture. [GM to H. W. Cross, August 19, 1945.]
Gorham Munson Biography
1896 Born May 26, Amityville, New York. Mother, Carrie (Morrow) Munson. Father, Hubert Barney Munson, Wesleyan class of 1892, and a Methodist minister.
1917 Graduated Wesleyan University. During his senior year, managed the Dramatic Association and was editor of the Wesleyan Literary Monthly. Sold his first article, based on his undergraduate thesis, on the Socialist conception of morality.
1917-1919 Taught English at the Ridgefield (Connecticut) School and at the Riverdale Country School in New York.
1919-1921 Lived in Greenwich Village and, with Hart Crane, Waldo Frank, and Jean Toomer, formed a literary group whose basic interests were in a new slope of consciousness.
1921 Married Elizabeth Delza of New York City, a professional dancer and teacher of dance, April 2.
1921-1925 Traveled and studied in Europe, living in Paris for a time. In Vienna in 1922, founded the little magazine Secession in collaboration with Matthew Josephson and Kenneth Burke. The magazine was published for two years, 1922-1924. Contributors included Crane, Frank, e. e. cummings, Malcolm Cowley, Marianne Moore, Wallace Stevens, and William Carlos Williams.
1926-1928 Editorial work: Grant Publications, Psychology magazine, and Bookman magazine.
1927-1966 Began teaching courses on literary topics at The New School for Social Research in New York city in 1927. In 1931, began experimenting with a workshop course in professional writing. This popular course, among the five best-attended, was repeated twice a year for more than thirty years.
1928-1950 Summer Writers' Conference Movement: Taught criticism for 13 sessions as a staff member of the Bread Loaf Writers' Conference at Middlebury College. For many years, wrote the annual preview of writers' conferences for the Saturday Review of Literature. A staff member of conferences at the University of New Hampshire, University of Connecticut, University of Colorado, University of Washington, and the Southwest Writers' Conference. Director of the University of Kansas City Writers' Conference, New York City Writers' Conference at Staten Island (Wagner College) and the Fairleigh Dickinson Writers' Conference.
1928-1960 Book Editor: Advisor to John Farrar, Doubleday, Doran, prior to Farrar's establishment of Farrar & Rinehart. Advisory editor with Thomas Y. Crowell beginning in 1934. Managing editor, national office, WPA Writers' Program, 1939-1940, and head of Library of Congress WPA Writers' Project, 1940-1941. Associate editor, Robert M. McBride & Company, 1941. Editor, Greystone Press, 1942-1943, Prentice-Hall, 1944-1948, Hermitage House, 1951-1955, and Thomas Nelson & Sons, 1955-1960.
1932-1945 Social Credit: Leading advocate of monetary reform through adoption of the principles of Social Credit. Founding member of New Economics Group of New York and the National Social Credit Association. American correspondent of the New English Weekly, 1932-1941. Editor, New Democracy, 1933-1936. General Secretary, American Social Credit Movement, 1938-1945. Author, Aladdin's Lamp: The Wealth of the American People, 1945.
1961-1966 Assistant Professor of English, Fairleigh Dickinson.
1966-1967 Senior Lecturer in English, University of California at Davis.
1967-1968 Fellow, Center for Advanced Studies, Wesleyan University.
1968-1969 Distinguished Visiting Professor of English, University of Hartford.
1969 Died, August 15, Middletown, Connecticut.
Collection Overview
The papers of Gorham Munson (1896-1969) deal almost wholly with his support of Social Credit and are confined to the years 1932 to 1945. There is almost no information about his career as a literary critic, book editor, and teacher of writing. The material includes articles, books, correspondence, pamphlets, and scrapbooks
The collection grew out of Munson's interconnected roles as organizer, publicist, fund-raiser, editor, promoter, lobbyist, propagandist, theorist, leader, and diplomat for a succession of Social Credit organizations from 1932 to 1945. Published materials provide the best documentation of the development of the theory of Social Credit in England, Canada, the United States, Australia, and New Zealand. The politics of individual and factional differences within the American movement is represented best by the files of correspondence.